Okay, let's get started.
Cool. Um, so as a recap of last week,
uh, we talked about multitask
reinforcement learning and how we might
want to have reinforcement learning
agents not learn just one task, but
multiple different things that might
correspond to multiple different reward
functions. And we saw that we can
formulate an aggregated MVP uh that
encapsulates all the different tasks
where you now are augmenting your state
with some sort of task descriptor like a
prompt or a goal or just an index
corresponding what to what they should
do. Uh, and the way that this worked is
we'd sample some task, um, kind of run
the policy in the MDP for that task,
sample another task, and so forth. Uh,
and we would then get, um, yeah, get a
policy that could be able to, uh,
successfully achieve high reward in a
number of different MDPs or in another
way to view it, a single aggregated MDP
with this augmented state.
uh this is going to be a little bit
different from metal RL. So we'll see
that uh some differences here uh later
in this lecture. Uh and we also somewhat
briefly talked about goal conditioned
reinforcement learning. Uh and it could
just be simply viewed as a a special
case of multitask reinforcement learning
where each task is trying to reach a
goal state and the task descriptor
corresponds to that goal state. And so
if your states are images for example
then now you'll be passing as input both
the to the policy both the current image
and the goal image and you'll be trying
to reach that goal image or if your
state for example is a vector you'll be
passing in two vectors and each the task
is trying to reach some goal state uh
and you can construct different reward
functions if you have discrete states or
continuous states uh as some sort of uh
did you kind of reach that goal or reach
close to that goal uh And one of the
things that's kind of nice about this
goal conditioned formulation of
reinforcement learning is that you can
actually do it in a self-supervised way.
You don't need task descriptors. You
don't need a different set of tasks that
you've manually defined. You can just
use a bunch of different states uh as
kind of the tasks themselves. Uh and a
lot of different tasks can be formulated
as goal reaching tasks. Uh one thing to
note here is it can be pretty hard to
train. um but you'll be experimenting
with uh a simple goal conditioned uh
reinforcement learning setting in your
homework.
Okay. So for today uh we're going to be
talking about meta reinforcement
learning and specifically we'll be
talking about what that problem
statement looks like and um a class of
meta methods that I like to refer to as
blackbox metarl methods. Uh we'll start
to get get into um what these methods
look like and also some of the
challenges that they face.
So, what's the problem? Like, why do we
care about meta RL? Uh, why not just do
vanilla RL? So, um, say that you're
trying to figure out how to operate a
coffee an espresso machine that you've
never used before.
Um,
if you wanted to do that, um, well,
first, if you wanted a kind of a a robot
or a reinforcement learning agent to do
that, uh, it would probably take a lot
of data, a lot of attempts to try to
figure out how to, uh, make coffee. Uh,
because it's a pretty complicated task,
lots of different steps involved. Uh,
you have to do those steps in sequence.
Um, and also the reward signal that you
get for this sort of task probably isn't
going to be super detailed. Uh but as a
human, if you were to attempt this task,
uh probably um if you had a little bit
of instruction or some previous
experience making espresso, then you
could probably learn it in minutes uh or
maybe even less than a minute.
So if you think about reinforcement
learning, this gap between how quickly a
human could learn something and how
slowly it would take a reinforcement
learning system to learn it, uh this is
rather unsatisfying.
And if we think about like what is the
difference between a person and a
reinforcement learning system, uh one of
the big differences is that people
aren't starting from scratch. Uh people
already know how to move objects around
with their hands. They might already
know how to make coffee in other ways or
with other machines and they can
leverage uh that experience and also
some notion of like kind of like uh
semantic knowledge of like what to do if
someone tells you to pick up a cup and
put it somewhere um or to turn a knob.
and I could leverage that previous
experience in order to solve this
problem really really quickly in
compared to training a reinforcement
learning system from scratch.
Um and so [clears throat]
experience with similar tasks other
espresso making machines um either
espresso making on other machines or
just general like motor control
following instructions that sort of
thing can be very useful when trying to
solve a new task. Um and I mentioned
this as a kind of example with espresso
making but um this sort of framework of
not starting from scratch is really
general. So uh it applies to robotics
problems where you want to fa when
you're facing a new environment or
facing a new task. Uh but it's also
really faced by many reinforcement
learning systems. Um as another example,
say you want to solve a challenging math
problem that you haven't solved before.
Um, if you have experience solving
previous math problems, then you can use
that uh to more quickly solve a new
problem because you've learned some sort
of strategies that you might be able to
apply to the new scenario.
Okay, we're framing this question of can
reinforcement learning algorithms
leverage experience from previous tasks
in order to learn a new task with less
data and less experience.
In many ways, this problem is thought of
as a transfer learning problem where we
want to transfer knowledge, information,
experience from previous uh tasks to new
tasks.
And there's a few different formulations
and a few different kind of problem
settings that the research community has
thought about. One is um kind of a
fairly stand like a fairly simple setup
where you learn one task and then want
to learn a new task and you can just for
example train on one task and then
fine-tune on the new task and notions of
fine-tuning that we use in supervised
learning are also applicable to
reinforcement learning settings where
you could fine-tune a Q function to a
new task or fine-tune a policy to a new
task.
Although um the for this to work well
the tasks need to be quite similar to
each other.
Um we also talked about multitask
learning and you could also use
multitask learning for transfer to new
tasks. Uh and in particular if your task
if your prompt shares some structure if
it kind of exhibits um if it's just like
a task one, task two, task three, um
transfer is going to be harder. But if
it's something that has a lot of
structure like pick up a water bottle,
pick up a phone, pick up um a pen and so
forth, then uh you might actually be
able to have things transfer what's
called zero shot without any new
experience at all uh simply by passing
that prompt to the system and having it
uh kind of act according to that prompt.
Uh and then metal learning is often
concerned with instead of zero shot
transfer something that's called fshot
transfer where you with a little bit of
experience a few examples or a few
trials at a task can you uh adapt to
that task.
And
essentially the difference between
multitask learning and metal learning is
that it accounts for the fact that we're
going to be trying to adapt with a small
amount of data. And it does that during
the kind of original training process.
Uh and another way of thinking about
this is that instead of having the task
descriptor be like a prompt or an index,
uh the task descriptor might actually be
a data set itself. Uh like a set of
trials that you're going to be adapting
to uh in the context of some policy. Um
another word for this is sometimes in
context learning or fshot learning. Now
for this to work uh for the first
scenario to work you must have very
similar source and target tasks. Uh
whereas in some ways that um things get
a little bit easier and a little bit
harder for number two and number three.
Um they get easier in the sense that you
no longer have to have extremely similar
task. You said just have need to have a
distribution of tasks and be similar to
that distribution such that conceivably
the new task that you're trying to solve
should be within the distribution of
things that you've the tasks that you've
seen during training.
Um it gets a little bit harder because
you do actually need mult like a number
of training tasks not just a single
training task uh in order to get
effective transfer.
Okay, before we jump into meta RL, let's
look just look at a couple thshot
learning examples outside of RL and then
go back to the RL setting. So, actually
I picked this example so it's not like
trivial. There's other test data points
that are much much easier. Cool. Um, so
that's kind of the essence of a few shot
image classification problem where you
have some a small number of data points
and your goal is to classify a new data
point. Um, and typically if you were to
train from scratch on just six images,
you'd have no hope of being able to
learn a classifier, especially on
highdimensional images. But the way that
metal learning works is you can
construct other tasks for the machine
learning system to solve that have a
similar structure like other image
classification tasks. Train it to be
able to take as input a training data
set and a query image or a test input
and then predict a label uh and
basically constructing these each of
these fshot learning problems as a data
point themselves.
Uh now another example of uh fshot
learning outside of reinforcement
learning is in context learning in large
language models. Uh and what this looks
like is um here's just one example.
There's lots of examples of different
tasks you could do. Um in this case the
goal is given a sentence that's kind of
poor English input like I eated the
purple berries output good English input
like I ate the purple berries. uh gives
it in this case I think uh four or three
different examples of input outputs. Um
this is the training data set and the
goal is for a new input be able to uh
predict a good output uh for that for
that example. So here's another example
kind of of a fot learning problem and
again language models get things that
kind of look like this during training.
Um, one thing that's a little bit
special about language models is that
this sort of incontext learning, you
don't explicitly set up your training
data set exactly to match all of this.
Um, and it turns out that a lot of the
statistics of data on the internet leads
to this kind of this ability to react to
these few shot examples effectively. Um,
this is actually just a base model. I
think this is from GPT3. Uh, and so even
without any additional supervised
training, you get something like this.
Um, it doesn't it's not perfect. Doesn't
work all the time. Um but this is
another example of fshot learning.
Um and then in each of these examples
you can think of of the goal is trying
to train this sort of model that takes
as input uh a training data set um and a
new example X and makes a prediction for
that example uh based on both X and on
the training data. Yeah. Yeah. So the
question is uh in in context learning in
LLMs typically you achieve this sort of
model and this sort of fuh shot learning
through prompting by putting the the
data set in as as context or as part of
the prompt into the model. Um is that
how also how it works in meta RL?
Generally yes we're going to be looking
at that case in meta RL. There are
actually other methods where you can
accomplish this with well actually with
gradient updates as well um or with
something like that that looks like
nearest neighbors. uh the most
successful method in metar looks like
prompting and so that's what we'll be
talking about uh today.
Now let's look at a metarl example. So
um
say that we want to navigate mazes.
Uh and so our goal is we want to solve a
new maze
and we're an agent that's in this maze.
We don't get to like see we actually
don't even see this top down view. Maybe
we just have a first-person perspective.
And our goal is because this is a
reinforcement learning problem, it's not
just about outputting a label. Uh it's
actually also about collecting
experience in the environment.
And so kind of the goal is we'd like to
be able to very quickly solve a
reinforcement learning problem. And
we'll frame this as collecting a very
small training data set of one episode
or a few episodes. Um in this case, it's
kind of exploring the maze, trying to
find um where the goal is. Uh, and it
eventually it kind of starts in the
middle right here, explores over here,
and it eventually goes to the goal right
here.
And after we explore, we'd like to be
able to have a policy that is able to
solve the maze uh just in this case just
with a single episode of experience.
And again, if you were to do uh this
sort of thing from scratch that uh tries
to use just a single episode of
experience to get a policy that can
solve the task, uh this would be very
very hard. uh and instead the way that
metaro um frames this is by trying to
construct uh examples uh and try to
construct kind of a set of training
environments that facilitates this kind
of fast adaptation.
Now in comparison to the supervised
learning scenarios like I mentioned
we're now going to have be faced with
this exploration problem. We're not just
given a training data set and then make
a prediction based on that training data
set. We're actually constructing the
training data set ourselves with through
exploration
and we need to figure out how best to
trade off between exploring in the
environment uh versus being able to then
solve the task and how much time we
should spend exploring versus uh trying
to exploit what we know about the
environment.
So if this is our our goal um this is
what we'd like to be able to do at test
time. We'd like to be able to quickly uh
learn a new maze. Then to set our agent
up for success at meta training time, um
before we try to adapt to a new maze,
we'll try to learn how to efficiently
explore and solve many other MDPs that
are related. Um in this case, they can
be other mazes like this and so forth.
And these are each of the tasks that
we'll be training on in order to adapt
to a new maze. Cool.
Um, the other thing, uh, I guess one key
assumption here is that you need to have
like these new MDPs can't be completely
different from the MDPs that you saw
before. Uh, and the way that we can
think about that is they we should have
some sort of distribution over tasks and
these new MDPs that we're trying to
adapt to should be within the
distribution of tasks that we saw during
training.
Okay.
Maze navigation is like one example of a
meta RL task. Uh there's lots of other
scenarios as well. Uh so one um one
useful scenario uh that we've seen in
robotics is being able to adapt very
quickly to different trains, different
slopes uh for legged robot systems. This
is actually a really small legged robot.
Um,
but it's also applicable um, to larger
legged robots as well. And sometimes you
might actually be training on different
environments in simulation and then
adapting in the real world as just
another environment.
Uh, you could also have object
manipulation as different tasks uh, as
well in manipulation scenarios. Uh, and
then there's also a number of language
modeling scenarios where this is quite
applicable. Uh one example where meta
has been relevant is adapting to
different users with different
preferences. Uh where you give examples
of the kinds of things the kinds of
responses that they want in context. Um
and we'll also later see an example in
reasoning as well. Yeah. So the question
is like what is the key difference
between this sort of meta approach and
transfer learning where you're training
and then fine-tuning. Uh and the there's
a couple ways to view it. One is that
you're during this kind of training
process, you're actually explicitly
optimizing for transferability. You're
optimizing for the ability to adapt with
a small data set. And as a result of
that, uh you can get much faster
transfer. You can use a much smaller
data set. Uh and there are examples of
like if you use fine-tuning versus if
you use like fshot in context learning
or fshot adaptation, you can get much
more efficient transfer. Um and yeah, so
you get much greater efficiency. Uh and
the the way that you get that is by
providing the algorithm with a number of
different training uh tasks rather than
like just one training task that you're
feeding off of. Okay. Um so slightly
more formally uh we've talked about
multitask learning um where you try to
solve multiple tasks at once. You might
try to transfer to a new task from that
um but you're not optimizing for
transferability. uh with transfer
learning you're trying to solve some
target task after
uh solving some source task uh typically
by fine-tuning. Uh whereas in the
metalarning problem we have experience
from some training tasks and we want to
very quickly solve uh a new task.
Um and in the reinforcement learning
scenario these tasks are going to be
MDPs uh each with their own state space
actions based dynamics reward. Um and
there is this kind of nice um we see
kind of metal learning and supervised
learning and there's also um this kind
of a nice uh analogy between the two
where the main difference with metarl is
this exploration challenge.
Okay. Um and then diving into some
notation here. Uh we can view the meta
RL problem as basically being able to uh
with a small amount of experience
be able to learn a policy that can solve
the task and also to be able to collect
this experience itself. And so this
training data there's a couple there's
two different variants of the meta
problem. Um, in the first case, this can
correspond to multiple rollouts from
some exploration policy.
And instead, you could also consider
this to be um just actually a few time
steps from your exploration policy. Uh
there's a bit of a continuum between
these two scenarios. You might want to
be able to adapt both online with a few
time steps um and with more and more
episodes with basically kind of a
growing data set. Um, but writing it
kind of explicitly uh as two different
things here uh to kind of
make it clear that there are some
problem settings where you want to adapt
really quickly online within an episode
and other scenarios where you're caring
a lot more about uh kind of multiple
trials uh of experience.
Um the last thing that I'll mention is
I've been writing it as a kind of an
exploration policy and a task policy. Uh
there are some scenarios where you might
train these and these might be separate
networks. There's other scenarios where
these could share parameters and
basically be the same network. So they
don't necessarily need to be uh
separated like they are on this slide.
Um and then the last thing is in so far
as we're learning this policy that's
conditioning on a training data set, you
can sort of view this as a task
identifier. Uh and from that standpoint,
we're then kind of more in a setting
that looks like multitask learning. Uh
so the question is when I say that it
has the test task should be in
distribution compared to the training
task does it mean it has to be the same
as one of the training tasks or um or
can it be a bit different? Uh it can be
a bit different. So uh the and we'll see
examples where it is different uh as
well.
So um let's talk about how to address
these problems. So, uh the the good news
is that there's a kind of a very uh
conceptually simple way to address this
kind of general problem statement. Uh
the bad news is that it can be
challenging to optimize in practice and
we'll talk about some of those
challenges in a bit. Um but conceptually
uh we can essentially uh train a
sequence model. Uh it could be a
transformer, any sort of neural network
with memory, a recurrent neural network.
Uh and
use this where um where basically
everything that's being passed into this
policy corresponds to the experience
that the agent has collected.
And so you're sort of you're basically
conditioning your policy on this
training data set. uh and then having a
policy output actions based off of the
data that it's seen so far in that MDP
and then training this um this sort of
uh the sequence model uh policy uh
across
all of the set of training MDPs that we
have. Um so here um this is the current
state. uh this sort of context or
training data set is going to get larger
over time as we collect more experience
in uh in a given MDP.
Um now a question for you uh there are a
couple differences between this and
simply using a recurrent policy in a
standard RL setup
uh or or using a sequence model in a
standard RL setup like using a
transformer. Um, does anyone have
thoughts on like what are some of the
differences between just between kind of
what I'm starting to talk about here and
simply using a sequence model as your
policy uh in kind of a standard RL
setup? Memory. Um, yeah. So, typically
in um in RL we often don't use memory
and here we're using memory. Um, so
that's that's like that's one thing. Um
but like compared to if we had used
memory in um in like a standard RL
setup, what else is different here?
Yeah. So one thing that we're doing here
is we're we're actually passing the
reward as input into the memory. And so
and that's a little bit different uh in
the sense that you're actually using
reward information from the current MVP
in order to try to get better at the
task. Uh this also means that actually
at test time or when we're trying to
adapt to a new task, we're also going to
be using the reward. Uh and in RL
settings, often times we don't
necessarily assume that we have uh the
reward when we're just deploying our
policy.
Okay. Any So that was kind of one main
difference. Any other differences?
Yeah. So the question is why are we also
not passing as input the actions? You
can pass as input the actions. Uh the it
depends on um like if your policy is
mostly deterministic then information
about past actions could be stored in
the memory as well because you are
predicting you generated those actions
and so in those cases you don't need the
actions. If you have a more stocastic
policy then the that sampling process
won't be necessarily in the memory and
in those cases it's good to pass input
the actions as well. Right? So the the
note was that the states and actions
might not be the same for different
tasks. And so one of the things that's
different here is we're actually
training this model across MDPs. And so
you might have a different state and
action space. You might have different
dynamics. And so because like one of the
big differences compared to standard RL
is that we're actually yeah we're
training this across MDPs. And there's
going to be differences in states,
actions, dynamics uh and rewards across
those MDPs.
Cool. There's actually also one other
difference. Um but the first thing that
we talked about is we're see that the
reward is passed as input. You might
also be passing as input actions and
this is trained across multiple MDPs. Uh
that's quite different from the typical
uh reinforcement learning setup. Now the
second thing that's also different is
that your memory is also going to span
across multiple episodes potentially. If
you're trying to actually learn um not
just within an episode but learn across
episodes then rather than having your
current policy simply have memory within
an episode uh you will be maintaining
any sort of hidden state or any sort of
memory um not just within your episode
but across multiple episodes.
Um so in terms of what this algorithm
maybe I'll leave this up here um in case
it's useful in terms of the algorithm uh
what this looks like is we will uh
sample
a task or an MDP
uh so maybe this let's call this MDP
uh TI
uh and then we're going to run our
policy in that MDP for multiple
episodes.
So let's say run
uh pi uh in our task or MDP for
n episodes.
So this is rolling out this right here
and it's going to have memory across
those n episodes.
Uh and then optionally if we have if
we're using an off policy algorithm with
a replay buffer then we would store the
uh the episodes in a replay buffer.
And then lastly we're going to optimize
update our policy to optimize the
rewards. uh and so we will be
updating pi and specifically we
are going to be maximizing the sum of
rewards like the typical RL objective
but it's going to be across all of the
tasks in our task distribution. So um
we'll have some sum over tasks I uh in
in some mini batch uh and then also the
uh expected sum of rewards. Uh so this
would be an expectation under our policy
of the sum of rewards over different
time steps.
Now the this is a pretty simple
algorithm. Uh it looks a lot like
reinforcement learning. We're simply um
the main thing that's different is that
we're going to be doing this
optimization across multiple MDPs and
we'll be our policy will have memory
across a set of episodes. Uh usually and
usually this is going to be pretty
small. uh because if if it was large, if
it was like a thousand episodes, it's
going to be hard to store that in the
context of um of a model like just
because your memory will start to
increase uh substantially.
Um so what that looks like is you have
uh this like neural network has uh
multiple episodes uh and then you'll be
kind of rolling it out for multiple
episodes taking actions and then you'll
start collecting for a new MDP. So
you'll cut your memory when you start to
collect for the new MDP that you've
sampled. So you sample a task, roll out
the policy for end episodes, in this
case n equals 2 in this diagram. um
under the dynamics and reward function
for that MDP.
Then store in your replay buffer. Often
times you'll have a different replay
buffer for each task and then optimate
update your policy to maximize the
discounted return for all tasks that
you've collected for and then repeat
this process uh in order to continuously
get a policy that's better at doing this
sort of in context adaptation.
Yeah. So the question this a good
question. So, does um the question is
does it know that it's starting a new
episode like at this uh position right
here? Uh you could use a position
encoding. Uh in practice, you're also
going to have a big like a probably have
a discontinuity in your state and so you
might just be able to see that like your
current state is very different from the
past state and that might also tell it.
Uh but yeah, you could have some sort of
token to also tell it that it's a new
episode. Um the question is are we
randomizing S1 across the different
episodes? uh when you're rolling out the
policy uh you will when you start a new
episode you'll sample that that will be
a different sample from the initial
state distribution uh and so s1 I guess
it's maybe a little confusing s1 here it
might be different from s1 here s2 is
very likely different from s2 here and
so forth
cool and then the outcome of this is
you'll have a policy that should be able
to adapt uh across episodes with
experience from those episodes uh and it
should be able to on its own actually
decide on the best exploration
exploitation trade-off. Uh and the best
exploration exploitation trade-off is
going to depend on the number of
episodes that you give it. Uh if if n is
two, then it has two episodes to
maximize rewards as quickly as possible.
And if it and if it needs to explore,
it'll explore as quickly as possible. If
n is a little bit larger, then you've
given it a little bit more budget to um
it still wants to maxim like explore
quickly and efficiently if it can
because then it can get higher rewards
later, but it might have slightly more
budget to explore. Uh and so you'll get
um one of the things that's like pretty
cool about this when you optimize this
whole thing end to end is that it will
make decisions on um on whether or not
to explore or to exploit. uh and it'll
make those decisions in a way that's
informed by whatever gets it the highest
reward.
Then after this sort of training
process, after you've trained it on uh
multiple MDPs,
then you can you can actually then roll
out your policy in a new task. Uh so
at test time
you will then give it a new task. So
you're in some new MDP
uh TJ
and
you can take the policy that was trained
and roll it out in um in that MDP. So
roll out
pi in
that MDP uh with those states, actions
and rewards and so forth. Um and so
sample new task, roll out that policy.
You want to roll this up out for up to
end episodes. Uh if you roll it out for
longer, um all bets are off in terms of
what it might do. Uh you could also um
yeah you could also have a variable
number of episodes that you uh use
during training if you want to be able
to handle variable numbers of episodes.
Um but yeah this would be like uh for n
episodes or for up to n episodes.
Cool. Um so in terms of actually
implementing this, there's a few
different architectures and optimizers
you could use. So you could use like a
vanilla recurrent neural network. Uh
some of the first works on meta
reinforcement learning did this. Uh and
they used um algorithms. This is I think
before PO existed or was introduced.
They used an algorithm that's somewhat
similar in nature in terms of the
assumptions as PO. Uh there's also a
model that uh a paper that before
transformers were really popular used
self attention um and also 1D
convolutions. You can think of it sort
of as a transformer um and optimized
this uh and you can actually note that
they do also pass the actions as input
um in in this particular scenario. Um,
one other thing, uh, we'll talk about
this a little bit in, um, a bit more
later, but you can also, uh, instead of
using a transformer or an RNN, you could
also use a feed forward network, um, and
then average across, um, average the
embedding. Uh, this is sometimes called
a deep set. Uh, and it's has its own uh,
benefits. It's actually pretty
computationally fast because you can
parallelize everything. um and also
actually surprisingly expressive uh for
what it can do. Um so let's look at some
examples. So um we'll look at this
example that was using something that's
kind of um a bit like a transformer uh
and they were use trying to learn how to
visually navigate a maze uh specifically
new mazes that the agent had never been
in before. They trained it on a thousand
small mazes
and they tested it on held out mazes
that the agent hadn't seen before. And
they tested it actually on both on small
mazes and on large mazes. This is
actually a scenario where they were able
to see some extrapolation to tasks that
were outside of the distribution of what
it was trained on. Um so this is what it
looks like. So this is at test time. Uh
and you can see that the agent it just
is like exploring around this
environment looking for where the goal
is. It only gets these images as input.
And on the right we can see the trace of
the exploration. So it started in the
middle, explored over here, it explored
down here, and eventually found the
goal. And then after that exploration
episode, we're still we still have
memory from that previous episode. And
it's able to uh using that memory, it's
able to then be able to kind of go
directly to the goal um
based on its experience in that maze.
Um so kind of watching that again.
Whoops. Um
it's this is the first episode and so
this is kind of the first episode of
rolling out this policy. Uh it's
choosing to explore because it doesn't
know where um where the goal is in this
maze. It also doesn't know the layout of
the maze. Uh and so we see it explore
here. And then in um in the second
episode, it chooses to go straight to
the goal because it decided that it
already explored uh the extent of the
maze. Uh here's an example in a larger
maze. So the agent starts over here um
and
it explores in the top part um doesn't
see the goal
um and realize that the kind of this is
a dead end. It doesn't need to explore
it further and then it ends up seeing
the goal here and then after that it is
um it goes straight to the goal after
that first episode. Uh and so in this uh
training example uh n equals 2. Uh so
they trained it just with to be able to
explore and exploit after two episodes.
Cool. And then quantitatively they
looked at the average time to find the
goal uh in both the first episode and
the second episode. uh they compared to
using a random policy uh which
occasionally does happen upon the goal
uh and using an LSTM architecture and
this more kind of self attention and
convolution architecture and they found
that with the small mazes um even within
the first episode they were able to do a
lot better than random that means that's
because it's actually exploring
efficiently and then eventually often
finding the goal uh and then it's able
to ex like find the goal faster in the
second episode after learning where the
goal is and about the maze in the first
episode. And we also see that it does
significantly better than a random agent
in the large mazes. Uh and in both cases
using kind of the self attention
architecture is better than using an
LSTM architecture which is another
memory architecture. Yeah. So the
question is is the reward to find the
goal and if so why is it optimized to
find it as fast as possible? Um so the
reward is to find the goal. Uh I I don't
remember the exact structure of the
reward. Uh the it's optimized to find it
quickly. There's a couple ways that that
lead to it to optimize to find it
quickly. Um
the in this particular case, uh I
believe they're using discounted
rewards. And so the discount factor um
instead of being like this, you have uh
you're optimizing for discounted
rewards. So there's a discount factor
right there. And the discount factor is
not one, it's like probably like 0.95 or
0.99. uh and so that objective will be
higher um if you get the reward sooner
rather than later. Yeah. So the question
is um what is passes input to the model
and yeah exactly so it's video uh from
the previous episode the actions from
the previous episode and one up
basically everything up until the
current time step which is any previous
episodes and everything so far in that
episode. So it's all of the video frames
and then also all of the actions and all
of the rewards uh as well. Yeah. So the
question is um where in the algorithm
are we exploring exploration versus
exploitation and the um here because um
it basically all comes down to this
objective for both of them and the
insight is that
the the the agent doesn't know
um doesn't know much about the task. It
doesn't know well depending on the the
training tasks. Um in this case it
doesn't know what what maze it's in. and
it doesn't know the structure of the
maze and that sort of thing. And so it's
actually not even it's not able to get
high reward until it starts to explore
until it finds like where the goal is
for example. Uh and so by optimizing
just end to end for reward you're
incentivizing it to um like it's not
going to get high reward without
exploration essentially. Yeah, we will
talk about that at um soon in like a few
lectures. But yeah, there's lots of
problems here because if when your
policy is bad and you're not getting
good rewards, it ends up being very
difficult to figure out uh a good
policy. Yeah. So the question is um
instead of uh
doing what we're doing, could it could
we just do regular RL and then do test
time training? Um the
so
in some ways language models with
recurrence
like it depends on how you view it but
in some ways you are already doing
something that kind of looks like metarl
if it has memory and it basically has
the ability to adapt depending on the
kind of the task that you're giving it.
Um and then yeah and then one important
component is if you're doing test time
compute you're allowing it to actually
like think through the problem. Uh now
test time comput is a very broad term.
So on the next slide uh we'll talk about
how you can actually use how meta is
relevant for test time comput. So let's
talk about that now. Uh so say that
we're solving different math math
problems. This is a canonical language
model example especially for test time
compute. Um and one example of a math
problem is trying to show this
inequality. Uh this is actually the same
I think possibly the same math problem
that Aval showed uh in his lecture. And
in some ways like trying to solve this
math problem is you can think of it in
some ways as an MDP itself. Uh in that
there's different strategies that you
might try to take to solve this math
problem and you don't know a priority
which strategy is going to help you
solve that problem. Uh like which kind
of which like where do you start? Like
do you try to for example do guess and
check? you try to uh like eliminate
terms in the equation uh and so forth
and ideally you'd be able to kind of
explore those different strategies and
then produce an answer based off of the
best strategy.
Um and it turns out that if you give um
so DeepSec R1 is a a language model that
uses test time compute in order to solve
math problems. And if you give uh R1
different math problems to solve um if
you give it a hard problem it kind of
thinks for a while um at some point uh
it like cuts off its test time uh the
test time compute because it doesn't
want to be thinking for too long for the
user. Uh and then it uh outputs some
explanation for the user. Um, and then
also if you give it a really easy
problem like 2 plus 2 equals question
mark, it actually also uh kind of thinks
through what the solution might be and
then gives a step-by-step explanation
for the answer. And so this is something
that is like clearly somewhat wasteful
to do probably uh unless this is somehow
a challenging problem. Uh, and so you
can actually use this notion of metarl
to try to optimize for test time
compute. And if you know that you're
going to be doing test time compute at
test time, then basically bring that
into the training process and um
encourage the model to efficiently use
that test time compute efficiently
explore different strategies such that
ideally on easy problems it is uh trying
to output an answer as quickly as
possible. And for harder problems it's
it's thinking as much as it needs
including possible exploration um until
it then tries to exploit and give an
explanation.
Uh and so um this this paper here was a
paper that explored that. Um they found
that when they uh were trying to
explicitly uh optimize for um effective
test use of test time compute, they were
able to get higher performance with the
same number of tokens uh and also uh
actually reduce the number of tokens
needed to get the same performance uh so
that you aren't for example uh using up
a ton of tokens on simple problems. Um
so that's a use case of metarl in uh or
ideas for metarl in language models.
Now a quick digression um and this will
actually lead us into a different way of
thinking about metarl.
So we've talked about multitask policies
where we condition on a task descriptor.
Um so maybe we want a robot to stack in
different locations or a robot to walk
in different directions. And we've
talked about policies that take as input
experience and then kind of generate
actions based off of that that data set.
And if you were to think about how this
relates to multitask learning policies,
one way to think about it is that we're
but just doing multitask learning, but
now this data is our task identifier.
And this is it's something that actually
changes within a task. Um so it's the
analogy is not perfect. It's not
actually fixed for a given task. uh
because sort of thinking think about it
as conditioning on the task in so far as
experience tells you what the task
you're trying to do is cool. Um and if
you think about goal condition policies
um rewards are like you can sort of also
view meta as kind of a generalization of
goal condition policies because there's
a set of MDPs that are goal reaching
MDPs and then there's a broader set of
MDPs that are reward maximizing MDPs. Uh
and so um and then the other way to
think about this is instead of trying to
generalize to new goals, you can think
about metarl as trying to adapt uh to
new tasks with a small amount of
experience. Uh this would be kind of the
difference between zeroot generalization
in the goal condition case and kshot
generalization with like k episodes or k
time steps in the metarl case.
Now um so we've talked about how we
could view the experience as
the task descriptor Z or the prompt
essentially but there's actually another
way to look at it which is that if we
think about this policy with memory and
that has kind of the past memory and
then our current policy. If we were to
think about what information is being
passed right here to the policy,
this information is is presumably
information about the task.
And so, and specifically, um, when Zi
isn't part of the state, there's
ambiguity about what MDP you're trying
to solve and you're using that
experience to try to identify the MDP
that you're in.
Uh, and you can sort of think about it
as the policy needs to infer the task.
can use in for specifically some sort of
latent task descriptor from its
experience.
And so another way of looking at meta is
something where you are using your
experience to infer what the task is and
then conditioning your policy that's
acting at the current time step on um on
your current estimate of what the task
is.
Uh so you can think about it essentially
as meta is trying to in explore to infer
this unknown task and then perform the
task. I see. So you're asking like um
because we're going to be inferring the
task identifier, why don't we just give
it to the the learning system? Yeah. So
the main reason is that we
if if we if we don't have a compact way
of describing the task that the agent is
doing, then it may actually be like
challenging. Like we may not have a if
we don't have a good way to represent
it, then we're not sure what to pass
into the policy. And if we don't have a
good way of representing it, we can
always resort to just using an index
saying this is task one, this is task
two, this is task three. But if you do
that and then at test time you say this
is task 100 uh it's not going to be able
to generalize in that scenario and and
do anything about that scenario about
that task. Uh whereas experience like
conditioning on experience is something
that could generalize where it can
actually be able to use um use kind of
the more continuous space of of states
rewards and so forth in order to figure
out a new task. Um, so it comes down to
representations and you could sort of
view this as like learning a Z
representation uh like learning like a
continuous vector that's representing
our tasks.
Now um in multitask RL we talked about
how there was this um
we talked about how uh when if you like
formulate some state space that it
corresponds to the original state space
and the the the Z vector then you get
this aggregate MDP. Uh and so the result
of this is
uh still an MDP
uh just with a new state space and and
like new dynamics to account for this
new state space. Uh and so there's a
question of like uh for metar
is there an aggregate MDP
and
this would be for metar
and in this case we're not providing ZI
in the state and so there's actually
like um inherently
uh it's actually partially observed. You
don't actually know what the task is.
You're trying to explore and figure that
out from experience. Uh and so there
isn't actually an aggate aggregate MDP
that you could think about. Uh instead
there if you wanted to try to aggregate
it into a single decision process, it
would have to be a partially observed
MDP or a POM DP. uh and it's actually a
special kind of pom dp um where uh we
talked about before where you have like
a some sort of partially observed markup
decision process where you can't
actually observe S uh
and the you have actions and instead of
observing S you observe some
observations
uh that are some function of S. uh the
that that would be kind of the general
palm dp case. Uh one thing that's a
little bit special about um about the
meta thing is the only thing that you
can't observe is what the task is. uh
and so
it's an it's basically a pond dp where
this hidden state space can be defined
as the observation and the task
identifier
and if you can infer the task identifier
from experience then you can essentially
view it as a way of trying to infer the
underlying state space uh as a way to
solve the pom dp.
Um so this is basically kind of another
way of looking at uh the meta all
problem. It's basically like a partially
observed markoff decision process. Now
there's an um a meta all method that we
actually talked about uh we I had showed
an architecture diagram that um that was
actually explicitly trying to output um
Z's and it was actually outputting some
distribution over Z's because at the
very beginning you actually don't know
what Z is. uh you have some kind of
prior belief over what Z is. And then as
you get more experience, you're going to
have a better and better estimate of
what Z is. And so if you represent a
distribution over this kind of latent uh
task representation, then um you can you
can do kind of cool things with that.
We'll see that in in a bit. And so this
uh particular algorithm is looking at
continuous control problems uh where
different tasks corresponded to walking
at different directions running at
different velocities uh and also
different physical dynamics. So being
able to adapt when the friction is
different um or the inertia of of the
robot system is different. The other
thing was that everything what we saw
before was using like a PO style
algorithm which is uh somewhat off
policy but not very off policy. uh it's
kind of more on policy than off policy
in some ways because it's not using a
replay buffer of past data.
Um and with metat training algorithms
you can adapt really really quickly. Uh
but the training process might be really
slow if your base algorithm is fairly on
policy. Uh and so
as a kind of question hopefully this
should be a straightforward question.
Um, if your base algorithm for updating
the policy at step four, if that's an
off policy algorithm, do you expect that
to be more or less efficient than if you
used an off policy or then if you used
an on policy base method? Yeah, more
efficient. So um if you're using a
replay buffer and using that replay
buffer to update your memory your policy
with memory that should be a lot more
data efficient during this metatraining
process at meta at kind of at test time
when you're adapting the efficiency is
going to be similar. So this is just
talking about the the efficiency for
actually training this sort of in
context uh learning system.
Uh and so if you look at um if you
actually look at the curves like over
this this training process right uh
right here the number of the amount of
data that you need in order to kind of
metalarn these kinds of systems you can
see that in blue if we're using um kind
of an off policy algorithm with a replay
buffer it's a lot more data efficient
learns a lot more quickly than um RL
squared and um and PMP which are using
well actually all three of these are
using uh base algorithms.
base algorithms that are more on policy
more like PO for example. Yeah. So the
question is um can I elaborate on what
specifically is in the replay buffer? So
uh the typically you'll have um well so
each replay buffer will have um
a sequence of episodes. Uh basically
each thing in the in the replay buffer
will be a sequence of episodes uh from a
given MDP. Uh and the um that includes
like the the states uh the actions, the
rewards. Uh and when you optimize this,
you'll need to oftentimes you'll have a
different repo buffer per task. So you
can sample a task here uh and then
optimize uh the reward for that task uh
um using the the memory from that um
from that that trajectory. Uh typically
the buffer instead of just storing
states and actions, you're storing full
trajectories together. uh because you're
going to be training a model with memory
and you need to be be able to provide uh
that trajectory as memory as input to
the policy.
Cool. Um so summary so far uh we've
talked about using these models to be
able to adapt to new MDPs. Uh they're
general, they're quite expressive. Uh
and there's also a variety of choices in
the architecture.
One thing is they're hard to optimize uh
because you're actually it needs to
figure out how to adapt uh from data and
there's lots of like there's lots of
different input features here that you
could try to pay attention to and the
model has to figure out what about those
like um those input videos that you're
passing as input for the maze navigation
is useful when you're then trying to
exploit and learn a policy. Uh so it's
it's because you're passing in so many
things as input, it's such a big uh
model, it can be hard to optimize for
that reason. And it can also be hard to
optimize from an exploration standpoint,
which we'll talk about right after this.
And then like the sample efficiency of
the metalarning process is going to be
inherited from whatever optimizer you
use in this last step right here. And so
if you use something like um like
vanilla policy gradient, it'll be
extremely data inefficient. If you use
something like PO, it'll be more stable.
uh but still fairly inefficient. If you
use something like SACE uh it will be
probably a lot more efficient although
you might need to tune the
hyperparameters more.
So now let's talk a bit about
exploration. Uh by exploration I mean
like uh exploration in context
exploration uh when you're trying to
explore a new task.
What we've talked about so far is trying
to optimize end to end for exploration
and exploitation with respect to the
final sum of rewards.
Um simple in principle it can actually
yield the optimal exploration
exploitation trade-off because you're
optimizing directly for some of the sum
of rewards. And that's really really
nice but it can be a really challenging
optimization and let's talk about why
that's the case. So
um let's look at a running example. So
say that you have uh some robot
that looks like this. And uh the robot
needs to uh find something. Uh and there
are some hallways
uh that the robot might need to go down
in order to try to find uh the thing
that it's trying to find. And different
tasks correspond to uh different
locations of the object that it's trying
to find. So in one in one task or in one
scenario it might need to it might be
all the way over here. Uh in another
scenario it might be over here and so
forth.
Uh and to help the robot out a little
bit. Uh we're going to introduce one
other thing which is that there's going
to be um like some piece of paper over
here. Uh, and that paper actually says
uh where the object is uh in words like
it says that the object like I don't
know maybe it's trying to find um like a
replacement light bulb or something like
that and it says the light bulb is in
like the fourth hallway at the end.
Okay. Um so here's our robot. Here are
the hallways. Um different tasks
correspond to navigating to the ends of
the different halls. And we have some
information about where to go. And if we
look at that um it it information will
be in the state about where uh where the
reward is for this task. Now
how do we actually learn how to explore?
So say that we were trying to collect
trajectories uh and trying to learn um
how to explore such that we can um get a
good uh get good behavior. So, say that
we
[clears throat] let's start with a
scenario where um we sampled the task
and maybe the task was to go to the end
of this hallway right here.
And say that we collected a um we
actually kind of just got lucky. We
collected a trajectory that just went
straight to that reward.
Now, in some ways that seems good
because we got reward for that. Uh, and
so that gave us um some reward uh and
that's like optimizing the objective
that we care about ultimate ultimately.
But the thing that's bad about this is
that the robot doesn't like the robot
got lucky and it doesn't actually know
how to repeat that in the future because
it um it didn't actually explore any
other alternatives.
And so this is going to be the way that
we can kind of view this is if it goes
to the end of the correct hallway, it'll
get positive reward, but the context
leading up to getting that positive
reward doesn't actually look different
than any other task. It kind of went
through here uh and it there's nothing
that kind of differentiates uh what it
did there which was like zero reward,
zero reward. Um than if the task for
example had been to go here or to go
here. uh and as a result it didn't
actually learn how to explore and it
didn't learn how to use exploration
information in order to solve the task.
And so this trajectory might might
actually be very helpful for learning um
for learning how to explore and learning
how to exploit.
Now let's say that we had
a different uh a different trajectory.
So we're exploring and let's say that
the agent uh instead of doing that it
had it maybe sampled the same task and
it went to the end of this trajectory
and then continued didn't see that and
then went to the end of this trajectory.
Um so that would be good in the sense
that it um it does actually have like it
did kind of rule out it has experience
that ruled out one task uh and now and
then it got reward for a different task
and so it's going to be teaching it
something about an exploration strategy
that works.
The downside is that exploration
strategy is quite suboptimal uh because
it would have been a lot more efficient
to then to first look at the
instructions and then go to the correct
position. Uh and so it's
somewhat good, somewhat bad. It provides
signal on a sub-optimal exploration and
exploitation strategy. Uh and so it's
perhaps better better than the first
trajectory that it did. Um but still not
ideal.
Um now let's consider a third
trajectory.
uh say that we are again collecting data
for for uh the meta process and let's
say that the agent um decided to like
look at the instructions and then just
like stay and like watch the
instructions.
Does anyone have thoughts on like
whether that would be like a useful uh
trajectory or not for the learning
process? Yeah, exactly. So it did
something useful but it doesn't get any
reward for that. like it only gets
rewarded until it if it did that and
then went here. Uh and so that's also
not going to be very useful for the
learning problem. And basically you only
like in the problem like this, you're
only going to actually be getting good
um like learning something useful about
how to explore and exploit if you
successfully
did the proper exploration behavior and
then did the exploitation behavior. And
if you do them in separate episodes,
then the um then you're not actually
getting good learning signal. Uh and
that means that you sort of have this
kind of sample complexity where you need
to actually get lucky and do both of the
two things at the same time in order to
get signal that helps you learn the
problem.
Um so basically it's hard to learn how
to explore and exploit at the same time.
Another way to um another example of
this is say that you're trying to learn
how to cook. uh you you have data in
previous kitchens. Your goal is to then
be able to quickly learn how to cook in
a new kitchen.
Now, in order to learn how to cook, you
need to find the ingredients. And if you
haven't yet figured out how to find the
ingredients because you have bad
exploration, then you can't learn how to
cook uh because you don't have the
ingredients with you. Uh then you're
going to get uh low reward.
Um, and then also if you don't yet know
how to cook, uh, because you haven't
like collected experience on that, then
regardless of the exploration you do,
you're going to get low reward. And so
you sort of have this chicken and egg
problem between learning how to explore
and learning how to solve the task using
that information. And so there's another
way to view this is this kind of
coupling problem where exploration and
execution or exploitation depend on each
other in order to be jointly successful.
So then the way to view end to end
training is that um it's great in that
like you can learn this optimal
trade-off but it can be extremely
challenging if you have a hard
exploration problem because you need to
figure out how to explore and exploit uh
and get learning signal uh that way. Um
the question is is that ultimate
challenge here that the reward is
sparse. So, uh, it's true that if you
had a dense reward, you, um, you'd be in
a much better place, uh, because
basically because you wouldn't really
have to explore, uh, you,
yeah, you would be able to, um, like you
wouldn't have to explicitly take actions
to explore
the um, and this really comes down to a
problem when exploration is hard. If
exploration is easy, this really isn't a
problem because you no longer have to
solve both exploration, exploitation.
you only have to solve exploitation.
So there's a couple solutions to this
and we'll start to talk about one
solution today uh and then on Friday
we'll talk about uh more solutions.
So
the second solution, I'm not going to go
into like complete detail on how these
work, but one solution here is instead
of optimizing just for endto-end reward,
you can add in auxiliary exploration
objectives to encourage it to uh to try
to actually figure out something um uh
more meaningful about the task. And one
approach here is to use what's called uh
posterior sampling um also called
Thompson sampling. And the the way that
this works is that uh we talked about we
talked about having um an algorithm
where you're trying to infer what the
task is. And if you have uh if you've
collected some experience so far and
you've inferred some distribution over
your task um in this case ZI is now kind
of some latent representation. It's not
a representation that's known.
Then what you could do is you could then
uh sample from this distribution and
then uh act as if that was kind of the
correct task.
So if you have um if you have like this
task inference procedure and then you
also have a policy that given an
estimate of Z uh is able to
generate actions
then what you can do is you can sample a
Z from this distribution and then sample
from this policy. And if you have
policies that can that are able to um
this starts to kind of decouple the
problem a little bit because if you have
policies that um for a given Z are uh
kind of do the task then you would
basically learn an exploration strategy
that is trying to uh kind of go down the
different um the different uh corridors
uh to find
uh the solutions. So, um, as an example,
this is actually a problem that looks
somewhat similar to the corridors where
you get a sparse reward. Um, if you
reach one of these circles and the
different circles correspond to
different tasks. And in this case, we've
sampled this uh this task right here.
And first, we sample um a Z from our
kind of prior over tasks without any uh
any we haven't collected any data yet.
So, we sample Z. We then run our policy
based on those different Z's and we get
exploration based on these. And then we
use that to infer what the task might
be. And so now we know that the task is
probably either over here or over here.
And so now you'll collect trajectories
that are lighter in color that are like
this one, this one, and going over here.
And then once you've actually collected
this trajectory, then you should
actually have a much narrower
distribution over the task because you
get positive reward here. And so then
you'll your policy or your Z
distribution will be narrowed out here
and you'll execute your policy according
to those Z's.
And so that's kind of one approach for
addressing this exploration problem. Uh
basically learning this represent this
latent representation over tasks and
then sampling from those tasks from that
distribution and acting accordingly
according to your policy for that task.
Um does anyone have thoughts on like so
there's some scenarios where this is
great and scenarios where this is not so
great. Um does anyone have thoughts on
when this sort of sampling might be bad
like what sort of MDPs this might not
work well in uh if you have a large
action space uh that could contribute uh
although it it isn't just having to do
with the action space because like if
you have a dense reward in a in a large
action space you'd be probably okay. So
if Z is out of distribution certainly
things will be problematic but even in
distribution there's scenarios where
this exploration strategy will be like
really bad. Yeah. So one so one scenario
where this might be work poorly is if um
if you start to see like some um some
reward uh but there might actually be
even even better reward in another
scenario. Uh you might kind of start to
exploit a little bit too early. Um
although it won't rule out those those
higher reward scenarios if it knows that
there are other tasks that might have
higher rewards. So I guess the kind of
the scenario that I was thinking of
where I think that this can be quite bad
is um it's actually a lot like this
scenario right here. So the strategy
that posterior sampling will learn in
this scenario is instead of looking at
the instructions, it's instead going to
go down each of the hallways and try to
find the reward. uh because it's trying
to explicitly explore by executing
policies corresponding to different
tasks. Uh and this will be especially
bad if the hallways are very long. Uh so
if the hallways are really really long,
like um I don't know, take days to
traverse, then what it's going to do is
it's going to spend days going down one
of them and then figuring out that it's
not the right one and then spend days
going down another one rather than
trying to seek out information that
might tell it about what to do.
Cool. So um for example, if the goals if
these goals are very far away and
there's some sign that tells you what
the correct goal is then um this is uh a
bad strategy. Now if that sign doesn't
exist uh then kind of it actually would
be a good strategy because you have to
go down those different quarters.
Okay. Um there's a couple of other
approaches that we can use as well uh
that include intrinsic adding intrinsic
rewards that try to um encourage it to
visit new states. uh and also trying to
visit states that help you distinguish
the dynamics and reward models for
different tasks. Um so we try to collect
data so that our model of rewards and
states are accurate. Um and with this
sort of approach you could actually get
exploration strategy that looks a lot
more efficient that looks something like
this compared to posterior sampling
that's trying to uh kind of just sample
the different uh trajectories for the
different tasks.
Um there's also scenarios where this
might be bad um if there's lots of
distractors um or really complex state
dynamics um but fortunately don't have
too much time to go over that now. So
these sorts of approaches are easier to
optimize than end to end. A lot of them
have some principle behind them uh but
they can be very suboptimal in certain
environments and it kind of depends on
the environment or the domain.